Welcome!
欢迎！欢迎
After last lecture, now that we can successfully move our character through our input, we can
经过上次的讲座，现在我们可以通过输入成功地移动我们的角色，我们可以
move up or down, and left or right, and we can even exit our climb state by pressing
向上或向下，向左或向右移动，我们甚至可以通过按
the climb action key.
攀爬动作键来退出攀爬状态。
Before we move on, there's one issue that I'd like to solve first.
在我们继续前进之前，有一个问题我想先解决一下。
So I'm gonna first lower the height of this mesh down, so that it'll be easier for me
所以我首先要降低这个网格的高度，这样我就可以更容易的
to get to the top.
到顶部。
So I'm gonna lower it down to 5.
所以我要把它降低到5。
And I'm gonna press play again.
然后我再按一次播放键。
So the scenario that I want to rule out is, when we reach a flat surface like this, I
所以我想排除的情况是，当我们到达一个像这样的平坦的表面时，我想立即停止攀登。
want to stop climbing right away.
我想马上停止攀爬。
It is quite weird that our character can move like this.
我们的角色可以这样移动，这是很奇怪的。
So in this lecture, we'll look at how we can do this.
所以在这个讲座中，我们将看看我们如何能做到这一点。
To achieve what we want, we need to make use of what we have.
为了达到我们的目的，我们需要利用我们所拥有的东西。
So the valuable information that we have is the current climbable surface normal.
因此，我们所拥有的有价值的信息是当前的可攀爬表面法线。
So I'm gonna use a simple vector to represent the normal.
所以我将用一个简单的向量来表示法线。
And another thing that we know is, we know we want to get rid of climbing when we reach
我们知道的另一件事是，我们知道当我们到达一个平坦的表面时，我们想摆脱攀爬。
a flat surface.
一个平坦的表面。
So the normal of this surface will be pointing up.
所以这个表面的法线将指向上方。
And this is also something called an up vector.
这也是一种叫做向上的矢量的东西。
So all we need to do is, we need to compare the surface normal and this up vector.
所以我们需要做的是，我们需要比较表面法线和这个向上的向量。
More specifically, we'll need to know the angle between these two vectors.
更确切地说，我们需要知道这两个向量之间的角度。
And if this angle here is smaller than certain amount, we should stop climbing.
如果这个角度小于一定的数量，我们就应该停止爬升。
So in here, I'm gonna name this angle theta.
所以在这里，我将把这个角度命名为theta。
This is just a common way to name an angle.
这只是一种命名角度的常用方法。
For doing calculation like this, you can name it however you like.
对于像这样的计算，你可以随心所欲地命名它。
And the math operation we need is something called dot product.
我们需要的数学运算是一个叫做点积的东西。
So same as cross product, this is another math operation that we can perform on two
因此，与交叉积一样，这是另一个数学运算，我们可以对两个
vectors.
向量。
And the return result of it.
而它的返回结果。
So if these two vectors, they are parallel with each other, the result will be 1.
所以，如果这两个向量是相互平行的，其结果将是1。
And if they are perpendicular, the result will be 0.
而如果它们是垂直的，结果将是0。
And if they are the exact opposite, the result will be -1.
而如果它们完全相反，结果将是-1。
But this is still not what we want.
但这仍然不是我们想要的。
We want to know the exact degree differences between these two vectors.
我们想知道这两个向量之间的确切度差。
And to get hold of that number, we'll need to understand how dot product is calculated.
为了得到这个数字，我们需要了解点积是如何计算的。
So in here, I have two vectors.
所以在这里，我有两个向量。
One is called vector A, one is called vector B.
一个叫做向量A，一个叫做向量B。
And how dot product is calculated is through something like this.
点积的计算方法是这样的。
So A dot B is equal to the length of this vector A multiplied with the length of vector
所以A点B等于这个向量A的长度与向量B的长度相乘。
B multiplied with cosine theta.
B乘以余弦θ。
So instead of this math equation, we are interested in theta.
因此，我们对theta感兴趣，而不是这个数学方程。
And let's look at how we can get hold of it.
让我们来看看我们如何掌握它。
So normally, when performing these kind of operations, we'll be using two unit vectors.
所以通常情况下，在进行这类操作时，我们会使用两个单位向量。
So they both have a length of 1.
所以它们的长度都是1。
And multiplying with two 1s really doesn't do anything to the final result.
而用两个1相乘，对最终结果没有任何影响。
So we can get rid of them.
所以我们可以把它们去掉。
And now this is our new equation.
现在这就是我们的新方程。
So all that's left there to do is to get rid of this cosine.
所以剩下的事情就是去掉这个余弦。
And we can do that by running our cosine functions on both sides.
我们可以通过在两边运行我们的余弦函数来做到这一点。
And this is our new result.
这就是我们的新结果。
And this is how we can get hold of the angle theta.
这就是我们如何获得theta角的方法。
Alright, that's the theory part.
好了，这就是理论部分。
Let's start coding.
让我们开始编码吧。
First, I'm going to close my project.
首先，我将关闭我的项目。
Then inside of the Visual Studio, I'm going to first go to the header file and scroll
然后在Visual Studio中，我将首先进入头文件，然后滚动到
up above this get climb rotation, I'm going to create a new function.
在这个爬升旋转上面，我将创建一个新的函数。
So it's going to return a pull.
所以它将会返回一个拉动。
I'm going to call it check should stop climbing.
我要把它叫做检查应该停止爬升。
Then I'm going to create a function definition.
然后我将创建一个函数定义。
And I'm going to place the function above this get climb rotation.
我将把这个函数放在这个获得攀登旋转的上面。
So place it in here.
所以把它放在这里。
And the first thing, I'm going to call the function inside of this physics climb.
首先，我将在这个物理学爬升中调用这个函数。
So I'm going to run an if check in here.
所以我将在这里运行一个if检查。
So if this check should stop climbing is true, we should stop climbing in here.
所以如果这个检查应该停止攀爬为真，我们就应该在这里停止攀爬。
We're going to do that later.
我们稍后要做的就是这个。
But now I'm going to finish implementing this function.
但现在我将完成这个功能的实现。
So scroll down.
所以向下滚动。
So the first if check, I'm going to check if climbable surfaces trace the results.
所以第一个if检查，我将检查是否可攀登的表面追踪结果。
So if this array is empty, then that means for some reason, during climbing, we're no
所以如果这个数组是空的，那就意味着由于某种原因，在爬升过程中，我们不再靠近
longer near a climbable surface.
不再靠近可攀登的表面。
Now likely that will happen.
现在很可能会发生这种情况。
If that happens, I'm going to return true.
如果发生这种情况，我将返回true。
So we should stop climbing.
所以我们应该停止爬行。
Once we get past this if check, then I'm going to create a const float.
一旦我们通过了这个if检查，那么我将创建一个常量浮点。
I'm going to call this dot result and it's going to equal to F vector dot product.
我将把这个点结果称为F向量点积，它将等于F向量点积。
So the two vectors that we are going to compare, the first one will be current climbable surface
所以我们要比较的两个向量，第一个将是当前可爬升表面的
normal.
法线。
The second one will be F vector, R vector.
第二个将是F向量，R向量。
So this is the return result of this dot product.
所以这是这个点积的返回结果。
And in order to get the degree difference, so I'm going to create another const float.
为了得到度差，我将创建另一个常量浮点。
I'm going to call this degree diff and it's going to equal to F math equals.
我将调用这个度差，它将等于F数学的等值。
So this is the r cross line function and passing this dot result.
所以这就是r交叉线函数，并传递这个点的结果。
And just like that, we can get hold of the angle of theta.
就这样，我们就可以掌握theta的角度了。
And the return result of this is still in radians and not degrees.
而这个返回的结果仍然是弧度而不是度数。
To convert this into degrees, we can run it through another function inside of F math.
为了将其转换为度数，我们可以通过F数学中的另一个函数运行它。
So it's called radian to degrees and add a parenthesis in here.
所以它被称为弧度转换为度数，并在这里添加一个括号。
And just like that, this is our degree difference.
就这样，这就是我们的度差。
All right, I'm going to print this out to prove this is working.
好了，我要把这个打印出来，以证明它是有效的。
So use the function debug print and the message is going to be degree diff.
所以使用函数debug print，信息将是度差。
And I'm going to append a string in here.
我将在这里添加一个字符串。
And there's one handy function inside of F string to help us convert a float into string.
在F字符串中，有一个很方便的函数可以帮助我们把浮点数转换成字符串。
So it's called sanitize float.
所以它叫做sanitize float。
And I'm going to pass in this degree diff.
我将传入这个程度差。
And since we're running this function every frame, I'm going to specify a color in here.
由于我们每一帧都要运行这个函数，我将在这里指定一个颜色。
So it's going to be a color cyan and the in key, I'm going to give it a value of one.
所以它将是一个青色的颜色，在键中，我将给它一个1的值。
All right, I'm going to compile first.
好吧，我先来编译一下。
And I don't have a successful compile and that's because I forget to return a value
我没有编译成功，这是因为我忘了在这个函数里面返回一个值
inside of this function.
在这个函数中。
So at the end of this function, I'm going to return false.
所以在这个函数的结尾，我将返回false。
Then I'm going to compile again.
然后我将再次进行编译。
All right, I'm going to launch my editor back.
好的，我将启动我的编辑器回来。
Go back to my editor, I'm going to press play in here.
回到我的编辑器，我将在这里按下播放键。
Then I'm going to go to a clamber surface, press F. And you can see now the degree difference
然后我要去一个攀爬表面，按F。你可以看到现在的度差
is 90 degrees.
是90度。
Now if I move up to somewhere around here and you can see if I move up a little bit
现在，如果我移到这里的某个地方，你可以看到如果我再往上移一点点
more and we're approaching 60 degrees.
我们就接近60度了。
Now if I move to a surface like this, the degree difference is zero.
现在，如果我移动到像这样的表面，度差是零。
And now with this piece of information, we can decide when we want to stop climbing.
现在有了这一信息，我们就可以决定何时停止攀登。
So I'm going to go back to Visual Studio and in here I'm going to do an if check.
所以我将回到Visual Studio，在这里我要做一个if检查。
So if this degree difference is less than or equal to 60.f.
所以如果这个度差小于或等于60.f。
If that's the case, I'm going to return true.
如果是这样的话，我将返回true。
So we should stop climbing.
所以我们应该停止爬行。
You can promote this to another member variable if you want, depending on the geometry in
如果你想的话，你可以把它提升到另一个成员变量，这取决于你的关卡中的几何图形。
your level.
你的水平。
All right, and one last thing, I'm going to go back to this fixx climb.
好的，最后一件事，我将回到这个fixx攀登。
So if this function returns true, I'm going to call the function stop climbing.
所以，如果这个函数返回真，我将调用函数停止攀登。
All right, I'm going to use live coding in here.
好的，我将在这里使用实时编码。
So first I'm going to press control plus shift plus s to save all.
所以我首先要按control加shift加s来保存所有。
Then I'm going to press control plus alt plus f11 to trigger live coding.
然后，我将按control加alt加f11来触发实时编码。
All right, live coding succeeded.
好的，实时编码成功了。
I'm going to press play again.
我将再次按下播放键。
And this time I'm going to climb up.
这一次我要爬上去。
And when I'm about to reach the flat surface, you can see I can exit the climb mode.
当我即将到达平坦的表面时，你可以看到我可以退出爬升模式。
I'm going to try again.
我打算再试一次。
So this time I'm going to move up through here.
所以这一次我要通过这里向上移动。
And it works.
这就成功了。
And with this kind of setup, this even works if we rotate this mesh a little bit.
在这样的设置下，如果我们把这个网格旋转一下，它甚至可以工作。
So let's say the mesh has an angle like this.
所以我们说这个网格有一个像这样的角度。
Now I'm going to press play.
现在我将按下播放键。
And I'm going to climb up.
而我要爬上去。
And just above, we are about to reach the top of it.
而就在上面，我们即将到达它的顶部。
We exit the climb mode.
我们退出攀登模式。
But everything is working as expected.
但一切都在如期进行。
I'm going to test it again.
我准备再测试一次。
So this time I'm going to rotate the mesh in this way.
所以这一次我要以这种方式旋转网格。
Then press play again and press f.
然后再按play，按f。
So we can climb up, no problem.
所以我们可以爬上去了，没有问题。
And we can exit the climb mode.
而且我们可以退出爬升模式。
And that's great.
这很好。
Everything is working as expected.
一切都在按预期进行。
So this is the math that I used to decide when to stop climbing.
所以这就是我用来决定何时停止攀爬的数学方法。
Once you figure this out, everything else should be pretty straightforward.
一旦你搞清楚了这一点，其他的事情就应该很简单了。
Feel free to refer back to the video if you need help.
如果你需要帮助，可以随时回看视频。
And it's time for you to do the same.
现在是时候让你做同样的事情了。
And I'll see you in the next lecture.
我们在下一个讲座中见。
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[音乐响起]
[音乐播放] [音乐播放]
[MUSIC PLAYING]